Guide to the Albert Prago Papers ALBA.135
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Albert Prago Papers
1937-1994
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Prago, Albert
ALBA.135
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Albert Prago (1911-1993) was born in New York City. He was scholar of Latin American history and Marxist economics, a college teacher and a veteran of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. After being wounded in Spain, he returned to the United States in 1938, and pursued a career in teaching and research. He published several books and articles on labor history, Latin-American history and the Spanish Civil War, earned a Ph.D. in history in 1976, and co-edited the 1987 anthology Our Fight with fellow Lincoln Brigade veteran Alvah Bessie. Much of the collection is comprised of material selected for inclusion in Our Fight. Another section consists of materials compiled by Prago for a course in American labor history. There are also original documents from the 1930s, mostly programs and handbills advertising events in support of the Loyalist cause. Of interest is a series of folders documenting the controversy among VALB members about Arthur Landis's contribution to the book International Solidarity with the Spanish Republic, 1936-1939.
Provenance
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Albert Prago was born in New York City in 1911. His parents were Latvian Jewish immigrants to the United States. Although his upbringing was not religious, he explained in an interview that his desire to volunteer to fight fascism had its roots in his Jewish cultural identity, an identity that is reflected in his later research on Jewish involvement in the Spanish Civil War. He joined the Communist Party in 1934. Before his departure for Spain in 1937, he was a charter member of Local 453, American Federation of Teachers, and taught social sciences in the Works Projects Administration adult education project. While a member of the Lincoln Brigade, he served both as Anglo-American editor of the International Brigades' daily newsletter and as the battalion's interpreter. Prago was wounded in the thigh by mortar fire during the second battle of Belchite in March 1938, and complications from osteomyelitis required him to spend over a year in the hospital before his recovery was complete.
After his return to New York in 1938, Prago concentrated his efforts on teaching and research, and remained deeply involved in radical political activity. He eventually earned a Ph.D. in history at the age of 65 from Union Institute and University, and taught at the Jefferson School of Social Science, Hofstra University, Cornell University's N.Y.State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Empire State College, and the New School for Social Research. His publications on the Spanish Civil War and the International Brigades include several articles exploring the roles of Jews and women in the conflict; these are collected in the 1987 anthology Our Fight: Writings by Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spain 1936-1939 co-edited by Prago and Alvah Bessie.
Prago retired to West Palm Beach, Florida. He continued to publish historical articles and remained actively involved with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade until his death from cancer in July 1993.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence, research and reference materials focused on the International Brigades and the Spanish Civil War. The bulk of the folders contain material selected for inclusion in Our Fight: Writings by the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spain 1936-1939 (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1987), edited by Alvah Bessie and Albert Prago. Most of the selections consist of photocopies of previously published articles and poems, but a few are original typescripts and/or previously unpublished material. Of interest are several folders containing submissions of the same type and format as the Our Fight materials but not found in the published work.
Notable materials dating from the 1930s and 40s include several programs and handbills advertising anti-fascist events and a memorial handbill and telegram on the death of SCW veteran Gerald (Jerry) Weinberg in World War II. The later part of the collection is perhaps most notable for the detailed correspondence and other documentation of the controversy among VALB members with regard to Arthur Landis's contribution to the book International Solidarity with the Spanish Republic, 1936-1939.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Subject Files, 1937-1994.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Several photographs were separated from the Albert Prago Papers in the course of processing.
Teruel, Battle of, Teruel, Spain, 1937-1938.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Periodicals.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Research (document genres).; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Drafts (documents); Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Prago, Albert
- Series I: Subject Files, 1937-1994.
  - Amblard, Manuel: "23 Years in Franco's Jails," from The Nation, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Labor History: Course Materials (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Labor History: Course Materials (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Labor History: Readings and Documents edited by AP, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Youth Congress: Message from George Washington Battalion, Copy of Irving Keith Postcard, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amery, Al: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Amnesty for Spanish Political Prisoners and Exiles, No. 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles by AP, undated, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Australian Spanish Civil War Memorial: Correspondence with VALB, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bailey, Bill: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bessie, Alvah: Contribution to Our Fight, [1952] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bessie, Alvah (aka D.A.N.): Contribution to Our Fight, [1938] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blair, John C.: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brower, Brock: "The Abraham Lincoln Brigade Revisited," from Esquire, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brunete Offensive: Excerpt from Log Book (photocopy), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burns, Paul: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - California Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Program from Tribute to Spanish Civil War Dead, "Camarada I.B.," by Leonard Cahn, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Carsman, Sam: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - C.H.: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clippings: Re: VALB, AP, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cogswell, Theodore R.: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Colodny, Robert G.: Contribution to Our Fight, [1958] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Colow, Maury: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1974, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Court Case Records: VALB, Subversive Activities Control Board, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Democratic Coordination, Spain: Press Release: Formation of, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - De Vries, Lini: Contribution to Our Fight, [1979] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - End McCarranism: On This We Stand Together: Pamphlet of Speeches from Rally, New York City, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Fajans, Irving: Contribution to Our Fight, [1952] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fisher, Harry: Brief Biography, Reminiscences: Marty Sullivan, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Geiser, Carl: Contribution to Our Fight, [1986] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gerlach, John R.: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Goff, Irving: IG Interviewed by Studs Terkel, from The Good War, [1984] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gordon, Joe and Leo (formerly Mendelowitz): Contribution to Our Fight, [1955] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Grunblatt, Jacques, M.D.: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hemingway, Ernest: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hughes, Langston: Contributions to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War: Articles, 1938, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Jones, James Moore: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kaufman, Sid: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Komodowski, Edward: Album Presented to Steve Nelson, Typescript Critical Account of the International Brigades from the Point of View of a Canadian Veteran (illustrated), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Landis, Arthur: Contribution to Our Fight, [1975] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Landis, Arthur: Controversy Re: Chapter in International Solidarity with the Spanish Republic, 1936-1939: Correspondence and Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Landis, Arthur: Controversy Re: Chapter in International Solidarity…: Notes and Exhibits C-J (?), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Landis, Arthur: Correspondence with AP, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Landis, Arthur: "The United States of America," chapter from International Solidarity…, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lardner, Jim: Contribution to Our Fight, [1938] (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - MacLeod, Don: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Martin, Fredericka: Contribution to Our Fight, [1937] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Memorial: Gerald (Jerry) Weinberg, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Memorial Program: J. Alvarez del Vayo, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Memorial Program: Orrin E. Feldt, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Memorial Resolution in Honor of Milton M. Cohen, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Negrin, Juan: Copy of Letter to Josef Stalin: Armaments Request, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Nelson, Steve: Transcript of Interview by AP, Tribute by Jessica Mitford, Contribution to Our Fight, 1975, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Neugass, James: Contribution to Our Fight, [1938] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Osheroff, Abe: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Our Fight: Editor's Notes, Blank Agreements, Miscellaneous Documents, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Poetry from the Spanish Civil War: Program from St. Clement's Poetry Festival, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Polish Jewish SCW Veterans Controversy: VALB Correspondence, 1986, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Prago, Albert: Contributions to Our Fight, [1979] (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Raven, Robert: Handbills for Los Angeles Program in Support of Loyalist Spain, [1938] (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rolfe, Edwin: Contributions to Our Fight, [1951] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Russian SCW Veterans: Victor Lavsky Correspondence with VALB, undated, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Segre, Sergio (Communist Party of Italy): Interview with VALB Delegation (Transcript), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Spain: Speeches to the Cortez, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Steck, Bob: "The Life and Death of Walter Grant," Article from The Volunteer, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Swedish SCW Veterans: Per Erikson Correspondence and Issues of För Ett Fritt Spanien (For a Free Spain), 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Thompson, Robert: Pamphlet re: "The Arlington Case", undated, [1966] (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Timpson, Arthur: Contribution to Our Fight, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Toral, María Teresa: Contribution to Our Fight, [1962] (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - U.S. Committee for a Democratic Spain: Flyers and Pamphlets, undated, 1963, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - VALB: Reports and Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Wachtel, Marion Merriman and Warren Lerude: Contribution to Our Fight, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Watt, George: Contribution to Our Fight, [1984] (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Weissman, Irving: Brief Biography, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Winston, Henry: "Spain in My Heart," Article from Political Affairs, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Wolff, Milt: Contribution to Our Fight, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)